<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tutorial>
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <description>A beginner's introduction to using ByteSkript's basic features and running scripts.</description>
    <author>Moderocky</author>
    <theme>
        <highlight>indigo-400</highlight>
        <background>white</background>
        <border>slate-900</border>
        <text>gray-700</text>
    </theme>
    <section>
        <node type="text">
            ByteSkript allows scripts to be run in a standalone environment from the command-line.
            Some versions may be attached to other applications (e.g. a Minecraft server) but for simplicity, this guide assumes you are using the basic version.
        </node>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Installing ByteSkript</title>
        <node type="text">
            The latest ByteSkript version can be downloaded from the <a href="https://github.com/Moderocky/ByteSkript/releases">GitHub Releases</a> page.
        </node>
        <node>
            There is one main executable Jar here, with commands.
            <ul>
                <li><b>run:</b> loads and runs user-created scripts.
                    This is the best option for creating and running scripts locally.</li>
                <li><b>jar:</b> compiles scripts into an executable jar file.
                    This is useful for building shareable versions of the program with no dependencies.</li>
                <li><b>compile:</b> compiles scripts into raw classes.
                    This is designed for language developers - these files are not directly executable.</li>
            </ul>
        </node>
        <node>
            This guide is written for using the <b>run</b> command.
        </node>
        <node type="info" mode="check">
            Make sure you have <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/technologies/javase/jdk17-archive-downloads.html">Java</a> installed.
            ByteSkript always runs on the latest Java version (currently 17.)
        </node>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Setting up Your Environment</title>
        <node>
            The first time you run ByteSkript it will create all the necessary folders and files for you.
            <ol>
                <li>
                    Place the downloaded <code>ByteSkript.jar</code> into an empty folder.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Run the Jar file with <code>java -jar path/to/ByteSkript.jar</code>.
                    Macintosh/Linux users can do this through terminal or <a href="https://coderedirect.com/questions/534005/script-to-run-jar-file-on-mac-os-x">by creating a clickable shell file</a>.
                    Windows users can do this through command prompt or by <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/394616/running-jar-file-on-windows">creating a clickable bat file</a>.
                </li>
            </ol>
            This should create <b>four</b> folders next to the ByteSkript jar.
            The <code>skript/</code> folder is the most important.
        </node>
        <node type="table">
            <thead>
                <tr>
                    <th>Folder</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <tr>
                    <td><code>skript/</code></td>
                    <td>This is where you put the scripts you write. Any <code>.bsk</code> file in this directory will be run.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><code>libraries/</code></td>
                    <td>This is where you can install third-party syntax libraries. Place the Jar/class in this folder.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><code>resources/</code></td>
                    <td>This is for adding extra text/data files that you want to package inside your compiled scripts. If you are using <b>run</b> you do not need to use this folder.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td><code>compiled/</code></td>
                    <td>If you are using <b>compile</b> or <b>jar</b> the compiled output will go here.</td>
                </tr>
            </tbody>
        </node>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Installing the CLI</title>
        <node>
            ByteSkript comes with a command-line interface that can be installed to your system, and will run the Jar file from anywhere through the <code>bsk</code> command.
        </node>
        <node type="info">
            Installers can be downloaded from the <a href="https://github.com/Moderocky/ByteSkript/releases">GitHub</a>. Not all systems support a command-line interface.
        </node>
    </section>
</tutorial>
